31. Fair fashion. American Halley Butfin traveled to Uganda in 2006 on a study trip.
She went there to learn about how young people could help build peace in the country after
a long period of war. While she was there, however, she also saw how important new businesses
could be to the process. Butfin visited traditional markets and thought about how she could help
the artisans who designed and made crafts to sell there. She wanted to help connect
them to people in the United States so they could sell more products, earn more money,
and improve their quality of life. She also wanted to help Ugandan women. In 2007, Butfin
met the woman who would become her trainer. That was the beginning of the One Mango Tree
Company. The company's purpose was to work with women artisans in Uganda, creating bags,
scarves, clothes, and jewelry to sell worldwide. The local artisans were trained and connected
to markets. These women were not the only people the company helped. Their children
were also offered scholarships. One Mango Tree was a unique idea when it first started
out. Since that time, however, many other companies have followed Halley Butfin's lead.
Working with local artisans in poor and troubled regions, these ethical fashion brands connect
people in many ways. The women who make the clothes can sell their products for more money
than they would receive otherwise. They can also learn how to become their own bosses
through business training programs. And the people who buy their products can wear them
proudly, knowing that their purchases have had a positive effect on someone's life.